Guide to the Baptist Union Theological Seminary Records 1866-1922
University of Chicago Library
Baptist Union Theological Seminary. Records
1866-1922
4.5 linear feet (7 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Baptist Union Theological Seminary was founded in 1865 by the Baptist Theolological Union. The Seminary eventually became the Divinity School of the present-day University of Chicago in 1892.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
In August 1863 a group of Baptist leaders met in Chicago and created the Baptist Theological Union. On Feb. 16, 1865, the Illinois legislature granted the Baptist Theological Union a charter for "the founding, endowment, support, and direction of an institution for theological instruction." That same year, Dr. Nathaniel Colver began to give instruction to a few students in his study. The Baptist Union Theological Seminary fully launched in 1866.
The formal work of the Baptist Union Theological Seminary began with the appointment of George W. Northrup as President and Professor of Systematic Theology. In the fall of 1867, courses in that subject as well as Ecclesiastical History and Biblical Literature and Exegesis were given to nineteen students in the Old University of Chicago’s Douglas Hall. On July 1, 1869, the Seminary dedicated its own building directly across the street from the Old University of Chicago. The Seminary provided theological education in English, Norwegian, Swedish, and Danish to Old University of Chicago and non-University students. Facing financial hardship in the mid-1870s, the Seminary sold its buildings near the Old University of Chicago and moved to donated land in the Chicago suburb of Morgan Park in 1877. The Old University of Chicago closed in 1886.
When John D. Rockefeller donated money toward the founding of the new University of Chicago, he made it a condition of the gift that the Baptist Union Theological Seminary become the Divinity School of the new institution. This took place formally on July 1, 1892. Since the establishment of the University of Chicago Divinity School, the Baptist Theological Union has continued its existence as a separate organization with its own Board, overseeing an endowment that provides support to the Divinity School.
Many Baptist Theological Union and Baptist Union Theological Seminary leaders were key to the founding and early history of the University of Chicago. E. Nelson Blake, President of the Board of the Baptist Theological Union from 1877 to 1893, was also a major donor to the new University of Chicago, and the first chairman of the University’s Board of Trustees. Edward Goodman and Thomas W. Goodspeed were also active in both institutions. The University of Chicago’s first President, William R. Harper, was a professor of Hebrew and Cognate Languages in the Seminary from 1879 to 1886. Dr. Eri B. Hulbert joined the faculty of the Seminary in 1881. In 1892, he became the first Dean of the Divinity School (until 1907).
Scope Note
The Baptist Union Theological Seminary Records include notes and correspondence from faculty and leaders of the Seminary, biographical and academic records of students, catalogs and brochures, and financial records.
Documents relating to the founding and operations of the Seminary may also be found in the records of the Baptist Theological Union.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago. Divinity School. Records
Baptist Theological Union. Records
Subject Headings
University of Chicago (1857-1866); University of Chicago. Divinity School; Baptist Theological Union (Chicago, Ill.); Baptist Union Theological Seminary (Morgan Park, Ill.); Theology -- Study and teaching
INVENTORY
- Seventy-Five Years: History of The Baptist Union Theological Seminary, 1867-1892, notes by C. E. Hewitt (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreement to donate land and money for the establishment of The Baptist Theological Seminary at Morgan Park, August 15, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Baptist Union Theological Seminary; early descriptive pamphlets and memorabilia, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Baptist Union Theological Seminary (Box 1, Folder 3A)
- Baptist Union Theological Seminary Annual Reports. 1869-1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Reports of the Board of Visitors to the Seminary 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Matriculation forms, alumni records, and course records for matriculants, 1886-1892 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Restricted Communion,” Sermon deliver at Union park Church, July 9, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Lectures on Doctrinal Theology,” lectures 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Lectures on Doctrinal Theology,” lectures 3-5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Lectures on Doctrinal Theology,” lectures 6-8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Lectures on Doctrinal Theology,” lectures 9-10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Colver, Nathaniel. “Lectures on Doctrinal Theology,” lectures 11-13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- “Notes on Lectures to the Theological Class of Chicago University, Rev. N. Colver, D.D., 1866” (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Reports of Professors Boise, Hulbert, and Price; recitation schedules, 1889-1892 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Conference of Representatives of Baptist Seminaries, minutes, New York, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- General Catalogue of the Baptist Union Theological Seminary, 1st edition, 1867-1890; 2nd edition, 1867-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Baptist Union Theological Seminary Library; charge book, circa 1880 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Alphabetical Catalogue of the library of the Rev. G.B. Ide given to Seminary, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Northrup, George W. “List of books in the library of Dr. George W. Northrup given to the U. of C. Library, May 1, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Northrup, George W. “Fragmentary Notes.” (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Northrup, George W. “Lectures on Church History,” 2 vol., winter, 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Notes on Theology by Dr. Northrup, Old University of Chicago (Chicago University), 1868 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Pattison, R.E. “Analysis of the Bible,” 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Alumni Association minutes; B.U.T.S., 1876-1892; The Divinity School of the University of Chicago, 1892-1922 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Class of 1888; Tenth Reunion, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Student Exams; Middle Theology, A-G, 1880-1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Student Exams; Middle Theology, H-W, 1880-1881 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Student Exams; Senior Theology, 1880-1881 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Student Exams; History of Doctrine, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Student Exams; History of Doctrine, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Student Exams; Hebrew, Middle, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Student Exams; Hebrew, Senior & Junior, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Student Exams; Hebrew, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1866-1870 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1870-1873 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1873-1875 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1875-1878 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1878-1881 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1881-1883 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1883-1886 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1886-1888 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1888-1890 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Catalogs and brochures, 1890-1892 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Biographical Records; Students of the Baptist Union Theological Seminary; Class History, 1865-1881; The Divinity School of the U. of C., 1893-1906. Bound volume (Box 7)